Raisbeck, Kenneth. Kenneth Raisbeck papers (MS Am 2604): Guide.
Kenneth Raisbeck papers,
1916-1938.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
This collection is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. See access restrictions below for additional information.
MS Am 2604
Raisbeck, Kenneth.
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Papers of American playwright Kenneth Raisbeck.
No accession number. Donor unknown; received: ca. 1949?
Materials probably belonged to Marjorie C. Fairbanks. Note in papers indicates donor information in letter of January 19, 1949 from A. Priest, (probably Alan Reed Priest, Harvard A.B. 1920), but this letter has not been located as of April 2008.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material.
This collection is not housed at the Houghton Library but is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. Retrieval requires advance notice. Readers should check with Houghton Public Services staff to determine what material is offsite and retrieval policies and times.
Kenneth Romaver-Ron Raisbeck (1899-1931) was born in Odell, Illinois, the youngest of nine children. He graduated from Bloomington High School in Bloomington, Illinois (Class of 1916) and Harvard College (Class of 1920, A.B. 1921). While at Harvard, Raisbeck was an assistant to (and later a good friend of) George Pierce Baker for his 47 Workshop play writing course and a close friend of American novelist Thomas Wolfe, whom he met in 1920. Raisbeck was said to be openly homosexual while at Harvard. In 1926, Raisbeck toured Paris with Wolfe and other friends, Marjorie Crocker Fairbanks (Mrs. Sydney Fairbanks) and Miss Helen Harding. At some point Wolfe and Raisbeck had an argument and continued their trips separately. Wolfe and Raisbeck never saw each other again.
Raisbeck became a playwright and screenwriter and lived in various locations in the United States. As a close friend of G. P. Baker, he spent time at Baker's summer home in New Hampshire. His plays consisted of Torches (1923), Rock Me, Julie which played for two weeks on Broadway in New York City (1931), and The lady of [in?] Spain which was never produced. Late in the 1920s he worked on screenplay scenarios in Hollywood and in 1931 he came East again. He was found dead in a Westport, Connecticut cemetery on September 30, 1931; the cause of death developed into a controversy but many said he was murdered by strangulation. The killer was never found.
Raisbeck was the model for the character Frank Starwick in Wolfe's second autobiographical novel, Of time and the river.
Marjorie Crocker Fairbanks was a close friend of Raisbeck, and for a time, the wife of Sydney Fairbanks. Sydney Van Kleek Fairbanks (1895-1985, Harvard (Class of 1917) A.B. 1920, JD 1925, AM 1933, PhD 1936) was the founder of the Harvard Poetry Society, a playwright, and author and former attaché to the Italian Ambassador. Austen Crocker Fairbanks was their child.
Biographical information taken from: Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938. The Starwick episodes; edited, with an introduction by Richard S. Kennedy. Akron, Ohio: Thomas Wolfe Society, 1989.
Organized into the following three series:
I. Correspondence with Kenneth Raisbeck
II. Compositions by Kenneth Raisbeck
III. Other materials
Papers include: letters from Raisbeck to his friend, Marjorie Crocker Fairbanks, and her husband Sydney Fairbanks, and child Austen Fairbanks; a few letters from Marjorie Fairbanks to Raisbeck; drafts of Raisbeck's plays: The lady of Spain. A play in four acts and Rock me, Julie! A play in three acts; extensive clippings concerning his death and the police investigation and scandal that ensued, and other materials.
See HOLLIS and OASIS for additional Thomas Wolfe materials and also Marjorie C. Fairbanks Correspondence and Notes on Thomas Wolfe (MS Am 1883.9) for additional papers concerning Mrs. Marjorie C. Fairbanks.
- I. Correspondence with Kenneth Raisbeck
  - Fairbanks, Austen Crocker, recipient. Letter and telegram from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1926., (1); 1 folder.
    From "Uncle Ken." Also spelled Austin.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C. Letters and telegrams to Kenneth Raisbeck, 1927-1931 and undated., (2); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1920-1921., (3); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1922., (4); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters and telegrams from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1925-1926., (5); 1 folder.
    Some autograph manuscript letters include typescript transcript copies.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters and telegrams from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1927., (6); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters and telegrams from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1928., (7); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters and telegrams from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1929., (8); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1930., (9); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Marjorie C., recipient. Letters from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1931 and undated., (10); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Sydney, b. 1895, recipient. Letter from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1920., (11); 1 folder.
  - Fairbanks, Sydney, b. 1895 and Marjorie C. Fairbanks, recipients. Letters from Kenneth Raisbeck, 1921 and 1923., (12); 1 folder.
- II. Compositions by Kenneth Raisbeck
  - Caballero: poster, ca. 1927., (13); 1 folder.
    Poster advertising French version of the Paramount film, The Gay defender (1927). Screenplay by Kenneth Raisbeck, Lay Harris, and Sam Mintz.
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. The lady of Spain. A play in four acts. Act I: typescript carbon, undated., (14); 1 folder.
    Typed on recto: "Kenneth Raisbeck, 508 Fairfax Hall, Cambridge 38, Massachusetts."
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. The lady of Spain. Act II: typescript carbon, undated., (15); 1 folder.
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. Late October: typescript poem, 1916 November 8., (16); 1 folder.
    Marked: Kenneth Raisbeck '20, Harvard Advocate Vol CII, No 3, page 48.
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. Rock me, Julie! A play in three acts: typescript carbon with manuscript revisions, undated., (17); 1 volume.
    Sheets have been bound in black covers.
    Written on inside of front cover: recto: "Kenneth Raisbeck,1437 5th Street, Santa Monica, California." Another address is crossed out: "1335 Lincoln Boulevard."
    Written on front fly leaf: "Kenneth Raisbeck his copy."
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. Rock me, Julie!: clippings, 1930 November 2 - 1931 February 14., (18); 1 folder.
    Includes advertisements and reviews for the pre-Broadway and Broadway production of the play.
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. Rock me, Julie!: program, 1931., (19); 1 folder.
    From the Royale Theatre production. Starred Helen Menken and Paul Muni, at the Royale Theatre, 45th Street, New York. Began at the Royale 1931 February 3. Directed by James Light, produced by Morris Green and Lewis E. Gensler.
  - Raisbeck, Kenneth. Torches: clipping, undated., (20); 1 folder.
    Announcement of play to be part of the Little Theatre Tournament in Boston.
- III. Other materials
  - Fairbanks, Austen Crocker. A death: typescript and typescript carbon, 1937-1938., (21); 1 folder.
    Two copies.
    A fictional version of the death of Kenneth Raisbeck.
    Original copy annotated: "Written by Austen at the Oakwood School 1937-1938.
  - Miscellany received with papers., (22); 1 folder.
    Includes: KR annotated New Yorker cartoon; numerous manuscript notes; business card for The Mispah Inn (Syracuse, New York); business card for William S. Kearns of the Connecticut State's Attorney's Office, County of Fairfield. manuscript notes concerning KR from back of a folder; and manuscript list of contents of papers.
  - Murder of Kenneth Raisbeck: clippings, 1931 October., (23); 1 folder.
  - Pfau, Edith Raisbeck. Edith's poem read at Kenneth's committal service Hampton, Illinois: typescript, 1931 October 6., (24); 1 folder.
    Edith Raisbeck Pfau was Kenneth Raisbeck's sister. Poem titled: Trees do not fret-- [first line]. Marked written in 1930.
    Also includes:
    Apocrypha. Wisdom of Solomon. chp. 3, Verses I to 9: typescript. Includes note that "Aunt Sarah" gave a quotation to mourners who regretted that Kenneth was alone on the night he died.
    Quotation from Walt Whitman's Leaves of Grass: "This is thy hour O soul!" [first line]: typescript carbon.